Gwendolen Margaret Carter, 1906-1991, Papers, 1943-1987
Smith College Archives
Gwendolen Margaret Carter Papers
1943-1987
Carter, Gwendolen Margaret, 1906-1991
RG 42 UUID:9ad21059-19d6-4f08-985e-381952bcd24c
1 box (0.4 linear ft.)
Smith College Archives Northampton, MA
Carter was a professor of government and scholar of African studies. Her papers consist of African Study Tours materials, biographical material, correspondence, course materials, photographs, press releases, publications, speeches, and articles.
Biographical Note
Gwendolen Carter, who once expressed her sole interest in life as "the world and all it contains," was born in Ontario in 1906. After obtaining her B.A. from the University of Toronto in 1929, she went on to obtain a master's degree at Oxford in 1935 and her Ph. D. at Radcliffe College in 1938. Before coming to Smith College in 1943, she was a lecturer and instructor at McMaster University in Ontario, Wellesley, Harvard, and Tufts, and worked for the Bureau of International Research at Radcliffe College.
Entering Smith as an assistant professor, Carter obtained full professorship in 1951 and held that position until her retirement in 1964, three years after she was made a Sophia Smith Professor. While at Smith she taught within the government department classes such as "Africa, South of the Sahara" and "The Political Structure of Africa." During her first sabbatical year in 1948-1949, Carter toured the British Commonwealth of Nations on visits to representatives of their departments of state, and later that year co-authored Major Foreign Powers, a book about the Commonwealth since the second world war. Several years later, on a leave of absence from Smith, Carter and a student assistant traveled 18,000 miles by car in South Africa doing research for her subsequent book, The Politics of Inequality: South Africa Since 1948, which is her best known work. She published four more books while still at Smith, in addition to a number of journal articles and pamphlets, and gave frequent lectures throughout the United States about the political states of Africa.
Carter was honored by the government of Kenya at its independence celebrations in 1963. The following year she left Smith to head Northwestern University's African Studies Center. By 1968, she had made 16 trips to Africa in 20 years, driven a total of 3,000 miles in the Congo, and authored, co-authored or edited 17 books. Because of the nature of her work, she was banned as an enemy of the state from entering South Africa for eleven years. Carter continued to visit Africa and publish work regarding its political systems throughout most of her life; an interview given in the New York Times in 1987 showed her optimism regarding racial equality in Africa to be undaunted. She died in 1991 at her home in Orange City, Florida at eighty-four years of age.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Gwendolen Margaret Carter papers contain brochures, press releases, newspaper clippings, and student lists from Carter's African Study tours, press releases and articles about Carter, biographical material, assorted correspondence, lecture notes, syllabi and exam questions from the courses that Carter taught at Smith, photographs and Christmas cards, publications, clippings and press releases about her sabbatical in South Africa, and transcripts of Carter's speeches. The bulk of the collection has to do with Carter's professional life, though there is some personal correspondence, and two Christmas cards.
The records are open for research according to the regulations of the Smith College Archives without any additional restrictions.
The Gwendolen Margaret Carter papers were donated to the Smith College Archives from a number of sources.
- African Study Tour 1957 (Box 695.1)
- African Study Tour 1959 (Box 695.1)
- African Study Tour 1961 (Box 695.1)
- Articles and Press Releases 1944-1987 (Box 695.1)
- Biographical Material (Box 695.1)
- Correspondence 1947-1982 (Box 695.1)
- Courses: "Africa, South of the Sahara" 1955-1963 (Box 695.1)
- Courses: "Lecture on Kenya" n.d. (Box 695.1)
- Courses: Notes for Lectures n.d. (Box 695.1)
- Courses: "Seminar on Comparative African Government" 1962-1963 (Box 695.1)
- Courses: Study Questions and Examinations n.d. (Box 695.1)
- Course: "The Commonwealth of Nations" 1960 (Box 695.1)
- Courses: "The Political Structure of Africa" 1955 (Box 695.1)
- Photographs 1957-1982, n.d. (Box 695.1)
- Publications 1943-1962 (Box 695.1)
- Sabbatical in South Africa 1952-1953 (Box 695.1)
- Speeches 1962 (Box 695.1)